So in 2011, I altered my name
في عام 2011، غيرت اسمي
so that I could participate in Far Right youth camp in Hungary.
لأتمكن من المشاركة في معسكر شبابي لليمين المتطرف في المجر.
I was doing a PhD looking at youth political socialization --
كنت أعد رسالة الدكتوراه عن التنشئة السياسية للشباب:
why young people were developing political ideologies
لماذا يطور الشباب توجهات سياسية
in a post-communist setting,
في أوضاع ما بعد الشيوعية،
and I saw that a lot of young people I was talking to
ولاحظت أن أغلب الشباب الذين تحدثت إليهم
were joining the Far Right,
كانوا ينضمون إلى اليمين المتطرف،
and this was astounding to me.
وكان ذلك صاعقًا بالنسبة لي.
So I wanted to enroll in this youth camp
لذا أردت التسجيل في هذا المعسكر الشبابي
to get a better understanding of why people were joining.
لأحصل على فهم أوضح حول سبب انضمام الناس إليه.
So a colleague enrolled me,
فقام زميل بتسجيل اسمي.
and my last name sounds a little bit too Jewish.
ولأن اسمي الأخير يبدو يهوديًا بعض الشيء،
So Erin got turned into Iréna,
تحولت (ايرين) لتصبح (أيرينا)،
and Saltman got turned into Sós,
وبدلاً من (سولتمان) أصبحت (شوش)،
which means "salty" in Hungarian.
والذي يعني "مالح" بالمجرية.
And in Hungarian, your last name goes first,
وفي اللغة المجرية يأتي الاسم الأخير أولاً،
so my James Bond name turned into "Salty Irena,"
لذا أصبح اسمي المخابراتي "أيرينا المالحة"،
which is not something I would have naturally chosen for myself.
وهو شيء ما كنت لأختاره لنفسي.
But going to this camp,
ولكن، بالذهاب إلى هذا المعسكر
I was further shocked to realize that it was actually really fun.
صدمت أكثر عندما أدركت أنه ممتع حقّا.
They talked very little about politics.
فقد كانوا يتحدثون قليلاً للغاية عن السياسة.
It was mostly learning how to ride horses,
وكان أغلب النشاط حول ركوب الخيل،
shooting a bow and arrow,
والرماية باستخدام القوس والسهم،
live music at night,
وموسيقى في المساء،
free food and alcohol,
وأكل وخمر مجاني،
also some air-gun target practice
أيضًا ممارسة التصويب ببندقية هواء
using mainstream politicians' faces as targets.
واستخدام وجوه السياسيين المعروفين كأهداف.
And this seemed like a very, actually, friendly, inclusive group
وقد بدا ذلك فعليًا كمجموعة ودية وجامعة،
until you started talking or mentioning anything to do with the Roma population,
حتى تبدأ في ذكر أي شيء متعلق بالغجر،
Jewish people or immigrants,
أو اليهود، أو المهاجرين،
and then the discourse would become very hate-based very quickly.
عندها يصبح الحديث مبنيًا على الكراهية بسرعة كبيرة.
So it led me into my work now,
وقد قادني ذلك في عملي الآن،
where we pose the question,
حيث نطرح السؤال:
"Why do people join violent extremist movements,
"لماذا ينضم الناس إلى الحركات العنيفة المتطرفة،
and how do we effectively counter these processes?"
وكيف نكافح هذه العملية بشكل فعال؟"
In the aftermath of horrible atrocities and attacks
في أعقاب حدوث أعمال وحشية أو هجمات
in places like Belgium, France, but all over the world,
في أماكن مثل بلجيكا، وفرنسا، وجميع أنحاء العالم،
sometimes it's easier for us to think,
أحيانًا يكون من الأسهل أن نفكر:
"Well, these must be sociopaths,
"مؤكد أن هؤلاء الأشخاص مختلون،
these must be naturally violent individuals.
وأن هؤلاء الأشخاص عنيفون بالفطرة،
They must have something wrong with their upbringing."
أو تم تنشئتهم بشكل خاطئ."
And what's really tragic
وما هو مأساوي حقًا
is that oftentimes there's no one profile.
هو أنه عادة لا يوجد حالة موحدة.
Many people come from educated backgrounds,
فالعديد منهم يأتون من خلفيات متعلمة،
different socioeconomic backgrounds,
وأصول اجتماعية واقتصادية مختلفة،
men and women, different ages,
رجال ونساء، من أعمار مختلفة،
some with families, some single.
بعضهم يملكون عائلات، وبعضهم عازبون.
So why? What is this allure?
فلماذا إذًا؟ وما هي هذه الرغبة؟
And this is what I want to talk you through,
وهذا ما أرغب في محادثتكم بشأنه،
as well as how do we challenge this in a modern era?
وكذلك كيف نواجه ذلك في العصر الحديث؟
We do know, through research,
نحن نعلم، من خلال الأبحاث،
that there are quite a number of different things
أنه يوجد عدد من العوامل المختلفة
that affect somebody's process of radicalization,
التي تؤثر على تحويل الشخص إلى متطرف،
and we categorize these into push and pull factors.
ونصنفها إلى عوامل دفع وجذب.
And these are pretty much similar for Far Right, neo-Nazi groups
وهذا يشبه كثيرًا جماعات اليمين المتطرف والنازية الجديدة،
all the way to Islamist extremist and terrorist groups.
وصولًا إلى الإسلاميين المتطرفين والجماعات الإرهابية.
And push factors are basically what makes you vulnerable
وعوامل الدفع هي ما تجعلكم عرضة
to a process of radicalization,
للتحول إلى التطرف،
to joining a violent extremist group.
والانضمام إلى الجماعات المتطرفة العنيفة.
And these can be a lot of different things,
ويمكن أن تكون هذه العوامل أمور عديدة،
but roughly, a sense of alienation, a sense of isolation,
ولكنها تقريبًا، الشعور بالاغتراب، والشعور بالعزلة،
questioning your own identity,
وافتقاد الهوية،
but also feeling that your in-group is under attack,
وأيضًا الشعور بأن جماعتكم عرضة للهجوم،
and your in group might be based on a nationality or an ethnicity
وجماعتكم قد تكون مبنية على القومية، أو العرق،
or a religion,
أو الدين،
and feeling that larger powers around you are doing nothing to help.
والشعور بأن السلطات العليا حولكم لا تقدم المساعدة.
Now, push factors alone do not make you a violent extremist,
وعوامل الدفع وحدها لن تحولكم إلى متطرفين عنيفين،
because if that were the fact,
لأنه إن كان هذا حقيقيًا،
those same factors would go towards a group like the Roma population,
فهذه العوامل تنطبق على جماعة مثل الغجر،
and they're not a violently mobilized group.
وهم ليسوا جماعة مبنية على العنف.
So we have to look at the pull factors.
لذا علينا النظر إلى عوامل الجذب.
What are these violent extremist organizations offering
ما الذي تقدمه هذه المؤسسات المتطرفة العنيفة
that other groups are not offering?
ولا تقدمه الجماعات الأخرى؟
And actually, this is usually very positive things,
وعادة تكون هذه الأشياء إيجابية للغاية،
very seemingly empowering things,
وداعمة بشكل كبير،
such as brotherhood and sisterhood
مثل الأخوية،
and a sense of belonging,
والشعور بالانتماء،
as well as giving somebody a spiritual purpose,
ومنح الشخص هدف روحاني،
a divine purpose to build a utopian society
هدف مقدس لبناء مجتمع مثالي،
if their goals can be met,
إذا تحققت أهدافهم،
but also a sense of empowerment and adventure.
وأيضًا الشعور بالتفوق والمغامرة.
When we look at foreign terrorist fighters,
عندما ننظر إلى الإرهابيين الأجانب،
we see young men with the wind in their hair
نرى شباب تعبث الرياح بشعرهم
out in the desert and women going to join them
في الصحراء، ونساء ينضممن إليهم
to have nuptials out in the sunset.
ليقيموا زفافًا وقت الغروب.
It's very romantic, and you become a hero.
أمر رومانسي للغاية، كما تصبحون أبطالاً.
For both men and women, that's the propaganda being given.
بالنسبة للرجال والنساء، هذه هي الدعاية المقدمة.
So what extremist groups are very good at
لذا ما تبرع فيه الجماعات المتطرفة حقًا
is taking a very complicated, confusing, nuanced world
هو أخذ عالم معقد ومربك ومتباين،
and simplifying that world into black and white,
وتبسيطه إلى أبيض وأسود،
good and evil.
خير وشر.
And you become what is good,
وتصبحون ما هو جيد،
challenging what is evil.
يواجه ما هو شرير.
So I want to talk a little bit about ISIS, Daesh,
أرغب في التحدث قليلاً عن داعش،
because they have been a game changer in how we look at these processes,
لأنهم غيروا طريقة نظرنا إلى هذه العمليات،
and through a lot of the material and their tactics.
من خلال الكثير من موادهم وخططهم.
They're very much a modern movement.
هم حركة حديثة بمعنى الكلمة.
One of the aspects is the internet and the usage of social media,
وأحد مظاهر ذلك هو الإنترنت واستخدام وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعية،
as we've all seen in headlines tweeting and videos of beheadings.
كما رأينا جميعًا في العناوين الرئيسية التغريدات وتسجيلات ضرب الأعناق.
But the internet alone does not radicalize you.
ولكن الإنترنت وحده لن يحولكم إلى متطرفين.
The internet is a tool.
فالإنترنت هو وسيلة.
You don't go online shopping for shoes
فأنتم لا تهمون بشراء أحذية عبر الإنترنت
and accidentally become a jihadist.
ثم تصبحون بالصدفة جهاديين.
However, what the Internet does do is it is a catalyst.
و مع ذلك، ما يفعله الإنترنت هو أنه محفز.
It provides tools and scale and rapidity
فهو يوفر الأدوات والانتشار والسرعة
that doesn't exist elsewhere.
التي لا توجد في مكان آخر.
And with ISIS, all of a sudden,
ومع داعش، وبشكل مفاجئ،
this idea of a cloaked, dark figure of a jihadist changed for us.
هذه الفكرة عن الجهادي المتخفي تغيرت لدينا.
All of a sudden, we were in their kitchens.
وبشكل مفاجئ، صرنا في مطابخهم.
We saw what they were eating for dinner.
ورأينا ما يأكلونه على العشاء.
They were tweeting.
كانوا يغردون.
We had foreign terrorist fighters tweeting in their own languages.
كان لدينا مقاتلين إرهابيين أجانب يغردون بلغاتهم.
We had women going out there talking about their wedding day,
وكان لدينا نساء يتحدثن عن يوم زفافهن،
about the births of their children.
وميلاد أبنائهن.
We had gaming culture, all of a sudden,
وأصبح لدينا ثقافة الألعاب،
and references to Grand Theft Auto being made.
وظهرت روابط بلعبة "جراند ثفت أوتو".
So all of a sudden, they were homey.
وأصبحوا فجأة مقربين.
They became human.
أصبحوا بشرًا.
And the problem is that trying to counter it,
والمشكلة أنه في محاولة لإصلاح الوضع،
lots of governments and social media companies
العديد من الحكومات وشركات الإعلام الاجتماعي
just tried to censor.
اكتفت بالمراقبة،
How do we get rid of terrorist content?
كيف نتخلص من المحتوى الإرهابي؟
And it became a cat-and-mouse game
وتحول الأمر إلى لعبة القط والفأر،
where we would see accounts taken down and they'd just come back up,
حيث يتم إغلاق حسابات لتعود بعدها مجددًا،
and an arrogance around somebody having a 25th account
وغطرسة حول شخص ما يملك 25 حسابًا،
and material that was disseminated everywhere.
ومادة منشورة بكل مكان.
But we also saw a dangerous trend --
ولكننا رأينا أيضًا توجهًا خطيرًا
violent extremists know the rules and regulations of social media, too.
فالمتطرفون أيضًا يعلمون قواعد وأنظمة وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعي.
So we would see a banal conversation with a recruiter
لذا يمكننا متابعة محادثة عادية مع مجنِد
start on a mainstream platform,
تبدأ في منصة برمجية شائعة،
and at the point at which that conversation
وعند النقطة التي تصبح فيها المحادثة
was going to become illegal,
غير مسموحة،
they would jump to a smaller, less regulated,
ينتقلون إلى منصة أصغر وأقل انضباطًا،
more encrypted platform.
وأكثر تشفيرًا.
So all of a sudden, we couldn't track where that conversation went.
وفجأة ، لم يعد ممكنًا متابعة مجرى المحادثة.
So this is a problem with censorship,
هذه هي مشكلة المراقبة،
which is why we need to develop alternatives to censorship.
ولذلك علينا تطوير بدائل لها.
ISIS is also a game-changer because it's state-building.
داعش أيضًا تغير أساليبها بسبب بنيتها كدولة.
It's not just recruiting combatants;
فهي لا تجند المحاربين فقط،
it's trying to build a state.
ولكن تحاول بناء دولة.
And what that means is all of a sudden,
وما يعنيه ذلك أنه بشكل مفاجئ
your recruitment model is much more broad.
أصبح نموذج التجنيد أكثر سعة.
You're not just trying to get fighters --
هم لا يبحثون عن محاربين فقط
now you need architects, engineers, accountants, hackers and women.
ولكنهم يحتاجون معماريين، ومهندسين، ومحاسبين، ومخترقي مواقع، ونساء.
We've actually seen a huge increase of women going
وقد رأينا عدد كبير من النساء يذهبن
in the last 24, but especially 12 months.
في الأشهر 24 وخاصة 12 الماضية.
Some countries, one in four of the people going over to join
وببعض البلدان، واحد من كل أربعة يذهبون للانضمام إليهم
are now women.
يكن من النساء.
And so, this really changes
وهكذا، بسبب ذلك تغير
who we're trying to counter this process with.
نوع الأشخاص الذين نرغب في مكافحة هذه العملية معهم.
Now, not all doom and gloom.
الآن، ليست كل الصورة كئيبة.
So the rest I'd like to talk about some of the positive things
لذا أود أن يكون بقية حديثي عن أمور إيجابية،
and the new innovation in trying to prevent and counter violent extremism.
والابتكار الجديد في محاولة منع ومكافحة التطرف العنيف.
Preventing is very different than countering,
والمنع يختلف كثيرًا عن المكافحة،
and actually, you can think of it in medical terms.
ويمكنكم التفكير بذلك باستخدام المصطلحات الطبية.
So preventative medicine is,
فالطب الوقائي هو
how do we make it so you are naturally resilient
كيف نجعلكم تعودون بشكل طبيعي
to this process of radicalization,
من عملية التطرف،
whereas that is going to be different
في حين أن ذلك سيكون مختلفًا
if somebody is already showing a symptom or a sign
إذا أظهر شخص ما أعراض أو إشارة
of belonging to a violent extremist ideology.
الانتماء إلى أيديولوجية متطرفة عنيفة.
And so in preventative measures,
في التدابير الوقائية
we're talking more about really broad groups of people
نتحدث عن مجموعات واسعة من الناس،
and exposure to ideas
والتعرض لأفكار
to make them resilient.
لجعلهم مرنين.
Whereas it's very different
وهذا يختلف كثيرًا
if somebody is starting to question and agree with certain things online,
عما إذا بدأ شخص بالتساؤل والموافقة على أمور معينة عبر الإنترنت،
and it's also very different if somebody already has a swastika tattoo
وهو مختلف أيضًا عن شخص ما لديه وشم الصليب المعقوف
and is very much embedded within a group.
ومنضم كليًا إلى جماعة.
How do you reach them?
فكيف نصل إليهم؟
So I'd like to go through three examples of each one of those levels
أود عرض ثلاثة أمثلة لكل واحد من هذه المستويات
and talk you through
وأحدثكم عن
what some of the new ways of engaging with people are becoming.
الطرق الجديدة للنقاش مع الناس.
One is "Extreme Dialogue,"
أحدها هي "الحوار المتطرف"،
and it's an educational program that we helped develop.
وهو برنامج تعليمي ساهمنا في تطويره.
This one is from Canada,
وهو من كندا،
and it's meant to create dialogues within a classroom setting,
ويقصد منه إنشاء حوار في فصل دراسي،
using storytelling,
باستخدام السرد القصصي،
because violent extremism can be very hard to try to explain,
لأن التطرف العنيف يصعب شرحه،
especially to younger individuals.
خاصة للصغار.
So we have a network of former extremists and survivors of extremism
لذا لدينا شبكة من المتطرفين السابقين والناجين من التطرف،
that tell their stories through video and create question-giving to classrooms,
الذين يروون قصصهم من خلال فيديو وينشئون تساؤلات في الفصل،
to start a conversation about the topic.
لبدء محادثة عن الموضوع.
These two examples show Christianne,
هذان المثالان يظهران (كريستيان)،
who lost her son,
الذي فقد ابنه،
who radicalized and died fighting for ISIS,
الذي تطرف ومات محاربًا لصالح داعش،
and Daniel is a former neo-Nazi
و(دانيال) وهو نازي سابقًا،
who was an extremely violent neo-Nazi,
والذي كان من النازيين الجدد شديدي التطرف،
and they pose questions about their lives and where they're at and regret,
وهم يطرحون الأسئلة عن حياتهم وأين هم وعلام يندمون،
and force a classroom to have a dialogue around it.
ويجبرون الصف على الحوار بشأن ذلك.
Now, looking at that middle range of individuals,
الآن، بالنظر إلى تلك المجموعة المتوسطة،
actually, we need a lot of civil society voices.
فإننا بحاجة فعليًا إلى العديد من أصوات المجتمع المدني.
How do you interact with people that are looking for information online,
كيف تتفاعلون مع الأشخاص الذين يبحثون عن معلومات على الإنترنت،
that are starting to toy with an ideology,
أو الذين يعبثون بأيديولوجية ما،
that are doing those searching identity questions?
أو الذين يطرحون تساؤلات عن الهوية؟
How do we provide alternatives for that?
وكيف نوفر البدائل لذلك؟
And that's when we combine large groups of civil society voices
وذلك عندما نجمع مجموعات كبيرة من أصوات المجتمع المدني
with creatives, techies, app developers, artists, comedians,
من المبدعين، والتقنيين، ومطوري التطبيقات، والفنانين، والكوميديين،
and we can create really specified content
ويمكننا إنشاء محتوى مخصص
and actually, online, disseminate it to very strategic audiences.
ونشره على الإنترنت لجمهور استراتيجي.
So one example would be creating a satirical video
أحد الأمثلة هو إعداد فيديو تهكمي
which makes fun of Islamophobia,
يسخر من رهاب الإسلام،
and targeting it to 15- to 20-year-olds online
ويستهدف الفئة العمرية 15 إلى 20 سنة على الإنترنت
that have an interest in white power music
الذين يهتمون بموسيقى السلطة البيضاء
and live specifically in Manchester.
ويعيشون في "مانشستر".
We can use these marketing tools to be very specific,
يمكننا استخدام هذه الأدوات التسويقية لنكون محددين للغاية،
so that we know when somebody's viewing, watching
لنعلم عندما يشاهد شخص ما،
and engaging with that content,
ويتفاعل مع المحتوى،
it's not just the average person, it's not me or you --
هو ليس مجرد شخص عادي، ليس أنا أو أنتم
it's a very specific audience that we are looking to engage with.
ولكن جمهور محدد للغاية، نتطلع للفت انتباهه.
Even more downstream, we developed a pilot program called "One to One,"
وتماشيًا مع الوضع، طورنا برنامجًا تجريبيًا يسمى "واحد إلى واحد"،
where we took former extremists
حيث أخذنا متطرفين سابقين
and we had them reach out directly to a group of labeled neofascists
وجعلناهم يتواصلون مباشرة مع مجموعة تسمى الفاشيين الجدد،
as well as Islamist extremists,
وكذلك مع متطرفين إسلاميين،
and put direct messages through Facebook Messenger into their inbox, saying,
ويرسلون رسائل مباشرة عن طريق "فيسبوك مسنجر"، تقول:
"Hey, I see where you're going. I've been there.
"مرحبًا، أنا أعلم إلى أين تذهب، فقد كنت هناك
If you want to talk, I'm here."
وإذا أردت التحدث، فأنا هنا."
Now, we kind of expected death threats from this sort of interaction.
وقد توقعنا تهديدات بالقتل بسبب هذا التفاعل.
It's a little alarming to have a former neo-Nazi say, "Hey, how are you?"
من المثير للقلق أن يقول أحد النازيين الجدد السابقين: "مرحبًا، كيف حالك؟"
But actually, we found that around 60 percent
ولكن في الواقع، وجدنا أن 60 بالمائة تقريبًا
of the people reached out to responded,
من الأشخاص استجابوا،
and of that, around another 60 percent had sustained engagement,
ومن بينهم، استمر 60 بالمائة في التواصل،
meaning that they were having conversations
ما يعني أنهم كانوا يتحاورون
with the hardest people to reach about what they were going through,
مع الأشخاص الذين يصعب الوصول إليهم عن ما كانوا يمرون به،
planting seeds of doubt
ويزرعون بذور الشك،
and giving them alternatives for talking about these subjects,
ويمنحونهم بدائل للتحدث عن هذه المواد،
and that's really important.
وهذا هام حقًا.
So what we're trying to do
ما نحاول فعله
is actually bring unlikely sectors to the table.
هو جذب القطاعات غير المحتملة إلى المائدة.
We have amazing activists all over the world,
لدينا نشطاء رائعون بجميع أنحاء العالم،
but oftentimes, their messages are not strategic
ولكن عادة، لا تكون رسائلهم استراتيجية،
or they don't actually reach the audiences they want to reach.
أو لا يصلون إلى الجمهور الذي يريدونه.
So we work with networks of former extremists.
لذا نعمل مع شبكات من المتطرفين السابقين.
We work with networks of young people in different parts of the world.
ونعمل مع شبكات من الشباب في أماكن مختلفة من العالم.
And we work with them to bring the tech sector to the table
ونعمل معهم لجذب القطاع التقني إلى المائدة،
with artists and creatives and marketing expertise
مع الفنانين والمبدعين وخبراء التسويق،
so that we can actually have a more robust and challenging of extremism
ليصبح لدينا شبكة أقوى وأكثر تحديًا للتطرف
that works together.
يعملون معًا.
So I would say that if you are in the audience
لذا أود أن أقول، إن كنت بين الحضور،
and you happen to be a graphic designer,
وصدف أنك مصمم جرافيك،
a poet, a marketing expert,
أو شاعر، أو خبير تسويق،
somebody that works in PR,
أو تعمل في العلاقات العامة،
a comedian --
أو كوميدي -
you might not think that this is your sector,
ربما لا تظن أن هذا قطاعك،
but actually, the skills that you have right now
ولكن حقيقةً، المهارات التي تمتلكونها الآن
might be exactly what is needed
ربما تكون هي ما نحتاجه تمامًا
to help challenge extremism effectively.
للمساعدة في مواجهة التطرف بفعالية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)